Register of the Anne Loftis Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Anne Loftis papers
1941-1976
71032
Loftis, Anne, 1922-
8 manuscript boxes, 3 phonotape reels (3.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, research notes, printed matter, and phonotape reels, relating to the evacuation and relocation of Japanese-Americans, 1942-1945. Includes oral history interviews of immigrants to California.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1922 Feb. 8 Born, New York, New York
1944 B. A., English, Smith College
1969 Author, The Great Betrayal: The Evacuation of the Japanese-Americans during World War II (with Audrie Girdner)
1973 Author, California: Where the Twain Did Meet
1977 Author, A Long Time Coming: The Struggle to Unionize America's Farm Workers (with Dick Meister)
1980 Author, John Steinbeck and Farm Labor Unionization: The Background of "In Dubious Battle" (with Jackson J. Benson)
1998 Author, Witnesses to the Struggle: Imaging the 1930s California Labor Movement
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of these papers are research materials compiled for the book Anne Loftis co-authored with Audrie Girdner in 1969, The Great Betrayal: The Evacuation of the Japanese-Americans during World War II. The collection includes correspondence, printed material, research notes, and phonotape reels. The papers document the evacuation and relocation of Japanese Americans during World War II, military service performed by Japanese Americans, and postwar efforts for restitution and civil rights for Japanese Americans. Also included are oral history interviews about immigrants to California and the 1906 San Francisco earthquake and fire.
The Notes series consists primarily of brief excerpts used to write The Great Betrayal. Occasionally chapter numbers are included in the folder title, but these numbers are sometimes misleading; chapter numbers written on the excerpts are probably more accurate. The bulk of the material appears to relate to Chapter One, "Crisis"; Four, "The Great Rejection"; and Five, "Evacuation". Abbreviations used by Loftis include JACL (Japanese American Citizens League), WCCA (Wartime Civil Control Administration), and WRA (War Relocation Authority).
While the Notes series is chiefly brief excerpts, the Sources and Research Materials series contains documents in their entirety. Included are clippings, government documents, notes of interviews of Japanese Americans and others who were involved in the evacuation and relocation in some way, notes from the diary and letters of Helen Kitaji, and general background material collected in the course of researching and writing The Great Betrayal. In most instances in both this series and the Notes series, the original titles of folders have been retained.
The bulk of the Newspapers series contains selected issues of the Pacific Citizen, the membership publication of the JACL, and a few issues of Gidra, a news magazine of the Asian American Community published in Los Angeles, which contain material concerning the history and activities of Japanese Americans. Also included are random issues of miscellaneous newspapers, including some in Spanish, that do not appear to relate to The Great Betrayal. The newspapers were typically retained in their entirety, but a few are annotated or have holes where articles were clipped.
The Phonotapes comprise five oral history interviews about the experience of immigrants in California and the 1906 San Francisco earthquake and fire. Individuals interviewed are (1) Dr. and Mrs. C. H. Loehlin, observers of immigrants from India; (2) Mrs. Walter Sharp and Mrs. Harris' mother, on the San Francisco earthquake; (3) Khatchik Minasian, cousin of William Saroyan, on immigrants from Armenia; (4) Carlton A. Sheffield, a friend of John Steinbeck and an observer of a variety of immigrants and Dust Bowl migrants in Marysville in the 1930s; and (5) Peter Jamero, son of immigrants from the Philippines. These interviews and the Newspapers series may be related to Loftis' second book, California: Where the Twain Did Meet, which concerns immigrant groups in the state.
Papers compiled by Anne Loftis for the book that she co-authored with Dick Meister, A Long Time Coming, are housed at the Stanford University Archives (Collection Number M0306).
The Hoover Institution Archives acquired the Anne Loftis Papers in 1971.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; California.; United States.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.
Genres and Forms of Material
Phonotapes.
Series Description
- Notes, 1941-1968. (Box 1-4)
  Clippings, excerpts, notes, arranged by subject in rough chronological order of events portrayed in The Great Betrayal
- Sources and Research Materials, 1941-1978. (Box 5-6)
  Clippings, correspondence, government documents, newsletters, notes, pamphlets, transcripts of speeches, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Newspapers, 1961-1976. (Box 6-8)
  Arranged alphabetically by title
- Phonotapes, 1970. (Box Tape cabinet)
  Five oral history interviews
Container List
- NOTES, 1941-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pearl Harbor in press (Folder 1: 1)
  - After Pearl Harbor experiences (Folder 1: 2)
  - Canadians/Peruvians (Folder 1: 3)
  - Extreme proposals against Japanese explanation (Folder 1: 4)
  - Skin color alone (Folder 1: 5)
  - Attitudes toward evacuation (Folder 1: 6)
  - Statements by outsiders (pro) (Folder 1: 7)
  - Tolan Committee (Folder 1: 8)
  - Criticism of WRA (Folder 1: 9)
  - Native Sons citizenship proposal (Folder 1: 10)
  - DeWitt order (Folder 1: 11)
  - Nisei position (Folder 1: 12)
  - Why evacuation? (Folder 1: 13)
  - Friends of Japanese Americans (Folder 1: 14)
  - Wartime
    - Propaganda (Folder 1: 15)
    - Relations Japan - U.S. (Folder 1: 16)
  - Anti-Japanese spokesmen (Folder 1: 17)
  - JACL (Folder 1: 18)
  - American Legion (Folder 1: 19)
  - Fishermen (Folder 1: 20)
  - Alien Land Law and escheat cases (Folder 1: 21)
  - Property Chap 5 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Civil Service firings (Folder 1: 23)
  - Senate Committee on Military Affairs recommendation (Folder 1: 24)
  - Prohibited zones/Restricted zones (Folder 1: 25)
  - Alameda (Folder 1: 26)
  - 1942
    - Goleta submarine and Los Angeles nervous (Folder 1: 27)
    - Freeze order (Folder 1: 28)
  - Curfew (Folder 1: 29)
  - WCCA Mar. 14, 1942 /WRA Mar. 18 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Bainbridge Island (Folder 1: 31)
  - Outside opinion 1943 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Dies Committee 1942 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Terminal Island (Folder 1: 34)
  - Marriages (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Privacy (Folder 2: 2)
  - Work at centers (Folder 2: 3)
  - Adult education (Folder 2: 4)
  - Trade affected (Folder 2: 5)
  - How it seemed after they left (Folder 2: 6)
  - Farm operation transfers and other evacuation procedure (Folder 2: 7)
  - Still tilling fields (Folder 2: 8)
  - May 8 - San Jose liquor licenses (Folder 2: 9)
  - Voluntary evacuation (Folder 2: 10)
  - Leaving homes/Later losses (Folder 2: 11)
  - Chapter 5 Orders and movement (Folder 2: 12)
  - Evacuation
    - Zone II (Folder 2: 13)
    - Stories (Folder 2: 14)
  - Trains (Folder 2: 15)
  - Hawaiians (Folder 2: 16)
  - News and news from outside (Folder 2: 17)
  - Friends outside visitors (Folder 2: 18)
  - Poston riot (Folder 2: 19)
  - Manzanar riot (Folder 2: 20)
  - Observers (Folder 2: 21)
  - WAR - Eisenhower (Folder 2: 22)
  - Coddling - later (Folder 2: 23)
  - Breakdowns? (Folder 2: 24)
  - Settling down (WRA words) (Folder 2: 25)
  - Sending for things (Folder 2: 26)
  - Shift of power (Folder 2: 27)
  - Relationship with outside (Folder 2: 28)
  - Family life (Folder 2: 29)
  - The human mix (Folder 2: 30)
  - Camp education (Folder 2: 31)
  - Co-ops (Folder 2: 32)
  - Institutional psychology (Folder 2: 33)
  - Health and medicine (Folder 2: 34)
  - Camp government (Folder 2: 35)
  - WRA - Evacuee relations (Folder 2: 36)
  - Vigilantism (Folder 2: 37)
  - Censorship - other than news (Folder 2: 38)
  - Japanese culture allowed in camps (Folder 2: 39)
  - The Great Rejection/1942 FDR order and results (Folder 2: 40)
  - Polarization (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Renunciants deportation (Folder 3: 2)
  - Early army experiences (Folder 3: 3)
  - Attempt to open up service (Folder 3: 4)
  - Veterans (Folder 3: 5)
  - Volunteers (Folder 3: 6)
  - Japanese language 1942 and intelligence (Folder 3: 7)
  - Nisei in service (military) (Folder 3: 8)
  - Emotions aroused (Folder 3: 9)
  - Mrs. Roosevelt - Gila May 1943 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Jobs with administration (Folder 3: 11)
  - Services in camp (Folder 3: 12)
  - Law abiding in camp (Folder 3: 13)
  - Patriotic activity (Folder 3: 14)
  - Relocation (Folder 3: 15)
  - Tolerance at colleges (Folder 3: 16)
  - Temporary leaves (Folder 3: 17)
  - Student relocation (Folder 3: 18)
  - New York (Folder 3: 19)
  - The arts (Folder 3: 20)
  - Segregation after registration (Folder 3: 21)
  - Service and no-nos (Folder 3: 22)
  - "Definitions" (Folder 3: 23)
  - Kibei (Folder 3: 24)
  - Religion at centers (Folder 3: 25)
  - Humor (Folder 3: 26)
  - Incidents other camps (Folder 3: 27)
  - Tule Lake after segregation/riot (Folder 3: 28)
  - Differences in centers (Folder 3: 29)
  - Beautification and improvement/vegetable gardens (Folder 3: 30)
  - Seabrook Farms (Folder 3: 31)
  - Camp papers (Folder 3: 32)
  - Food at camps (Folder 3: 33)
  - Well-known artists (Folder 3: 34)
  - More permanent leaves 1942 on (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Breaking camp (Folder 4: 2)
  - Postwar vigilantism (Folder 4: 3)
  - Restitution (Folder 4: 4)
  - Issei today (Folder 4: 5)
  - Postwar
    - Housing (Folder 4: 6)
    - Employment (Folder 4: 7)
  - Immigration and naturalization (Folder 4: 8)
  - Welfare on return 1945 (Folder 4: 9)
  - Japanese Americans today (Folder 4: 10-11)
  - Japanese American leaders (Folder 4: 12)
  - Economics of discrimination/Social follows (Folder 4: 13)
  - Income 1960 (Folder 4: 14)
  - Intermarriage (Folder 4: 15)
  - Language schools today (Folder 4: 16)
  - Discrimination today/late 1960s (Folder 4: 17)
  - Social
    - Discrimination subtle (Folder 4: 18)
    - Action (Folder 4: 19)
  - JACL today (Folder 4: 20)
  - Sansei (Folder 4: 21)
  - Camps today (Folder 4: 22)
- SOURCES AND RESEARCH MATERIALS, 1941-1978 (Box 5)
  - General
    - Bibliography (Folder 5: 1)
      - Bancroft (Folder 5: 2)
      - Hoover Library (Folder 5: 3)
    - Correspondence (Folder 5: 4)
  - After Pearl Harbor (Folder 5: 5)
  - Camps under Internal Security Act of 1950 - since repealed (Folder 5: 6)
  - Educational aspect of the Japanese evacuation problem (Folder 5: 7)
  - Evacuation from Terminal Island (Folder 5: 8)
  - FDR Correspondence on evacuation (Folder 5: 9)
  - Interviews (Folder 5: 10)
  - Japanese American renunciant cases (Folder 5: 11)
  - Japanese Americans today (Folder 5: 12)
  - Japanese in Hawaii (Folder 5: 13)
  - Kitaji, Helen (Folder 5: 14)
  - Life in relocation centers (Folder 5: 15)
  - Nisei in the armed service and official communiqués (Folder 5: 16)
  - Open Forum (Folder 5: 17)
  - Pictures (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Pre-Pearl Harbor (Folder 6: 2)
  - Problems at time of evacuation 1942 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Property losses (Folder 6: 4)
  - Renunciation of citizenship, repatriates, restitution (Folder 6: 5)
  - Sentiment about Japanese returning to California from camps (Folder 6: 6)
  - Tea garden (Folder 6: 7)
  - Tule Lake Center where supposedly pro-Japan evacuees were segregated (Folder 6: 8)
- NEWSPAPERS, 1961-1976
  - General, 1961-1972 (Folder 6: 9-10)
  - Gidra, 1970 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Pacific Citizen
    - 1967 (Folder 6: 12)
    - 1968 (Folder 6: 13-14)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - 1970 (Folder 7: 2-4)
    - 1971 (Folder 7: 5-6)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1972 (Folder 8: 2-3)
    - 1973 (Folder 8: 4-5)
    - 1974 (Folder 8: 6)
    - 1976 (Folder 8: 7)
- PHONOTAPES 1970, 3 tapes (Tape cabinet)
  Sound recordings of five oral history interviews conducted by Anne Loftis
  - Sound recording of Dr. C. H. Lochlin and Mrs. C. H. Lochlin 1970 June 24, The Lochlins live at 1732 Buchanen St., East Marysville, California. Tape 1. Use copy reference number: 71032_a_0008175 part 1, number 1
  - Sound recording of Mrs. Walter Sharp and Mrs. Harris' mother undated
    They talk about the San Francisco earthquake. Tape 1. Use copy reference number: 71032_a_0008175 part 1, number 2 and part 2, number 1
  - Sound recording of Khatchik Minasian 1970 May 5, Tape 1. Use copy reference number: 71032_a_0008175 part 2, number 2
  - Sound recording of Carlton A. Sheffield 1970 June 7, Tapes 1-2. Use copy reference number: 71032_a_0008175 part 2, number 3 and part 3
  - Sound recording of Peter Jamero 1970 May 18, Tapes 2-3. Use copy reference number: 71032_a_0008175 parts 4-6